Let’s move now to capabilities.
In this case, we associate a list of permissions
to each domain/process. Each entry in the
list is a capability, a file (or another object),
and the set of rights associated with it.
Since two domains can have part of their capabilities
lists overlapping, they could use pointers
to point to other lists hierarchically.
Also in this case, we can have the common
read, write, and execute rights, as well as
other additional rights that are specific
to a certain system or operating system.
We can ask ourselves: how to prevent a user
from altering his/her capabilities?
One way is to use a so-called tagged architecture.
In this case, each word in memory (the word
is the unit of data used by the processor)
has a special bit (the tag) that, if set,
indicates the word contains a capability and
can only be changed when in kernel mode (so,
by an OS process or a trusted process).
A second way to go is to keep the capabilities
lists in OS memory, so user processes can
point to them but not alter them.
Finally, a third way to go, which is particularly
useful in distributed systems, is for user
processes to prove their rights are indeed
correct when using files maintained by remote
servers. This technique simplify the sharing
of files/rights in distributed systems.
Let’s assume we have a cryptographically
secure one-way function f (it means from x
we can compute y = f(x) but from y it is infeasible
to find out x). In this case, when a file
is created at the server, the server generates
a random number (called check) and returns
to the client the file id, the rights, and
f(file id/Rights/Check), without giving the
value of check back to the client but rather
storing it locally. When the client wants
to access the file, it shares the id, the
rights, and the value of f. The server recomputes
f taking the file id and rights from the client,
but the check from its tables. If the values
match, then the rights claimed by the client
are correct and the request can be honored.